[Music]
Good evening. I call the finance
committee meeting for March 24, 2025 to
order. Um, we're going to move out of
the agenda pattern slightly. Uh, we have
a, uh, special guest with us, a couple
guests perhaps, and service safety
director. Uh, would you like to
introduce and just Absolutely. Thank
you. So, we actually have with us this
evening our architect, uh, Melinda
Skoolie Caldwell, and she is here to
talk to us tonight about the city hall
renovation project and answer any
questions that council members may have
since we are going to be voting on this
legislation this evening. Thank you.
Would you like Melinda come to come up
at this show? All right. Well, Melinda,
why don't you go ahead and come up?
I will go ahead and let you just give a
quick uh brief history and overall uh
project description and then we can open
it up to questions that council has.
Okay. Well, we were happy to be selected
um to work on the Lancaster City Hall
back in 2022. Um we've been looking at
it off and on. Did initial um concept
estimates and budgets figuring out what
would make
sense. Sorry.
Um, and really paying attention to the
historic character as well as Hold on.
I'm so
sorry. We've got her choked up already
over the project.
Windows. Windows. Let's go choked up.
So, we're really looking at um what
makes sense for this building both
shortterm and long term. Um, Lancaster
is very fortunate. You have a beautiful
city hall
building and it's one that you have
taken good care
of over the last 100 plus years. So when
we're looking at historic buildings that
are owned by city entities, things are a
little different. You know, this isn't a
building the developer builds and then
plans on selling in 10 years. This is a
building you've already held on to for
100 years. We certainly hope you plan to
hold on to it for another hundred years.
So, we're not necessarily looking at
what's the cheapest solution for now.
We're looking at what is the best value
decisions we can make for this building
and the community looking at the next
hundred years, which means sometimes
spending a little bit more money now um
to save money uh long term and also
really trying to maintain the historic
integrity of this building. Um the
stonework is generally in fairly good
condition, though there's a few areas um
that have degraded over the years that
need some attention. Um and by paying
attention to those now and repairing
some things, we can save um bigger
maintenance or replacement costs later.
Um there are other things um like the
roof. Generally, the slate um some of
the slates in good condition, some of it
needs to be replaced. Um the membrane
roof that's up on the flat part of the
roof um is was past its expected life
expectancy when we were first up there
in 2022. It actually had a big slit in
it that was temporarily repaired. Um so
that's scheduled to be replaced. Um and
then also looking at while we are there
because there's a cost to having access
to things
um is working on the clock as well
because the clock needs some um work.
There's one face that has strapping that
is attaching across the inside of the
clock tower to keep it from falling out.
Obviously, that's a concern. That's not
a permanent solution. Um, so while we
have there's scaffolding and lifts and
things on site, really restoring that
clock, making sure um that it is um
going to last for a long time. Same
thing with the bell and the floors under
the bell. So, everything that we're
looking at um doing is repairs for the
long term. Um, we've done extensive cost
benefits analysises on multiple state
capitals and county courouses that have
similar problems. And really what it
comes down to is if you can do the
repairs right, the repairs that are
going to last a long time. Um, in the
end, you'll come out way ahead. You're
not going to be have to be back in front
of taxpayers asking them, you know, 10
years down the road. It's like, yeah,
we'd spent all that money. Yeah, I know
you still remember that, but now we need
to do this, too. We're trying to get in
there, do as much as we can for the
budget that you've set, um, and have
those repairs last as long as possible.
So, and so, if you'll recall back when,
um, Skullie Caldwell was hired to do the
assessment, they did bring back to the
city um, a full project that included
the interior and exterior uh, of city
hall for upgrades and renovations and
repairs. However, uh based on the cost,
the administration decided that we felt
it was best to proceed with the exterior
and not do any of the interior work with
the exception of the elevator because
that is a safety concern. So, we felt
that it was important to do the elevator
but then do the exterior of city hall so
that we can prevent any further damage
than what's already been done. Anything
that you want to add to that? I think
that's the main thing. Um the elevator
is definitely at the end of its life. So
it is time to replace it before it
entraps more people. So um which is
based on the uh life or the time that
that elevator was put in is kind of
typical what we see. We in addition to
exterior restorations, we've been doing
a lot of elevator replacements lately.
So um unfortunately it's time. So, and
so I know that we had sent to you a copy
of the estimate back when we introduced
the legislation and the estimate was for
everything that we are looking at
restoring or repairing on the exterior
of city hall and then again with the
elevator. So, at this time I would open
it up to any or I'll defer back to you
uh Chairman Wolfinger to take any
questions for myself or for architect
Melinda over here to answer. Yeah, I
think that probably makes sense. Um, I
guess we have one question. Yeah, at
couple of meetings ago, we had
conversation about this and the uh wood
windows came up and I'm an architect and
I do a lot of wood clad windows,
exterior clad aluminum interior wood and
just the concept of an interior exterior
wood finish to me seems like it just
lends itself to longterm maintenance
cost to keep the exterior protected. And
I think if I'm not mistaken on the uh uh
the downtown courthouse renovation
across from provisions, I think they
have aluminum clad windows on the
exterior. And that's a very historic
building as well in our city. And um the
thing that we were hearing back was that
Woodclad isn't historic, but I doubt if
anybody really looks at the county
courthouse downtown and says, "Wow,
those windows are not historic on that
historic building." So, is there any
potential for going with a a metal clad
wood window? So, part of the reason we
we're um we were getting away from
aluminum clad window wood windows is the
size of these windows. Some of these are
up to eight feet tall. Um they are very
large windows. They are really beyond
what the capabilities of um a commercial
wood aluminum cloud wood window
manufacturer can do easily and still
have them operate. Um so we we had um
when we were working on one of the state
capitals um they actually had us do a
study in depth that ended up being about
a 100page report doing very detailed
comparisons of his um historic historic
wood windows, aluminum cloud windows,
full aluminum windows um and even poss
the possibility of vinyl windows and
looking at all the different
characteristics and how they compared
and contrasted. And one of the things
that comes up with aluminum clad windows
is their one at their ability to handle
those very large openings. They use more
modern hardware. They use a block and
tackle system instead of traditional
weights and pulleys which um over time
cannot handle a window that size.
They're just not strong enough. Um and
the hard thing is then when they start
to fail, they don't have the ability to
be um necessarily repaired at that
point. You have to replace them. um
which is a challenge because uh as soon
as you're going to a commercially
manufactured product, you know, like any
um commercially manufactured pretty much
anything out there, you know, someone
makes a certain line of windows for a
couple years and then they change. Well,
if you need to replace one window, all
of a sudden that one window isn't going
to match because they're no longer
making that exact one. The benefit with
wood windows is yes, they you are going
to have to paint them every once in a
while. Um, we aren't looking at a u a
commercial wood window. These would be
custom wood. They're um aoa um is the
base manu the base wood that we're
looking at which is an acetylated pine.
Um which feel free to look it up. It has
a very um it's basically they take pine
and they pickle it which sounds crazy.
Um when I first got a sample of it, it
actually smells like pickles. Um, but
that basically acts as a preservative
for it. So, it can last a very long
time. Um, they've tested it. Um, and
it's up there with mahogies, um, which
is what we always used to use. Now,
mahogany is getting very hard to get.
It's also not that environmentally
responsible anymore. Um, so we've gone
to this, which takes a really good paint
finish. It lasts a long time. Um, and
the nice thing is if part of it breaks,
um, or rots, heaven forbid, um, but
something happens to it, you can call a
good carpenter and they can come out and
make you a piece, make you a new sash.
Um, they also still use the traditional,
um, weight and pulling method. So,
instead of ropes though, which you might
see in some of your older homes, they'll
use chains, um, which don't break. I'm
If anyone's had an old home that has
weights and pulleys with ropes, I know I
have about probably five in my house
that are broken. Someday I'll get around
to it when I'm not working on everybody
else's buildings. Um that, you know,
those do break. The the chains and
pulleys um don't. So, they can handle
that weight repeatedly. Um the other
difference we look at is um if you look
at some of the newer windows, they use
weather stripping and things like that
that historic wood windows didn't. we
can actually incorporate a lot of that
weather stripping into these historic
wood windows. Um so they'll have metal
weather stripping. Um they might have
bulb gasketing in certain places so
they'll seal up um just as well if not
better than an aluminum window. Um, the
other part of the reason that we've
started shying away from some aluminum
clad products too is some manufacturers,
depending on which one, have had um
problems with class action lawsuits
because water is getting into the window
and rotting behind the aluminum. Um, so
as a firm, we've kind of started getting
away from that because we don't want to
leave anyone in a position where you're
having to deal with aluminum clad
windows that are rotting. Um because
when you think something of being clad
in aluminum, you think of it, you know,
that not being able to happen.
Unfortunately, um that seems not to be
the case. Now, not all the manufacturers
are like that. Some of them make really
good products, but they still don't have
the same lifespan as a really good wood
window. Um the wood windows up in
Delaware County Courthouse, which we
restored a couple years ago, are still
the original wood windows from 1870.
So, and we've worked on them twice. So,
um the second time it was mostly a coat
of paint and a few pieces of glass here
and there. So, um they can last. Um the
nice thing is most of these windows
still have their original um frames
behind the aluminum. Um they've actually
gone in and removed some. Uh and the
good thing about that is that is old
growth wood that's even better than
whatever we can get now. So, the idea is
to restore those um replace it where
necessary um keep that old growth
material intact. So, you're also going
back to your original full window
opening. So, it's it's just a different
things for different buildings. So,
Sure. Okay. Well, thank you. You're
welcome. Other questions?
I do have one. Sure. Um, your original
bid for the wood windows was
930,6593
and I hear the arguments. That's fine.
What would the cost be of the aluminum
or vinyl? Um, well, I don't know that
you could get vinyl um approved here um
because of your historic overlays. an
aluminum one. If you're going to
aluminum window that actually meets the
historic character that I'm pretty sure
your historic commission would insist
on, it's not substantially less um
because you're having to go to you
wouldn't be going to um like someone
that makes commercial storefront
windows. You' be go you'd be going to an
aluminum um window manufacturer that
specializes in historic windows. um
which I have honestly um put in school
buildings because those school districts
I know have no ability to maintain
anything. That's whether I like it or
not, that's the case. Um the those
aluminum windows um are probably 75% or
so of the cost of the wood, but they're
only going to last 40
years. And at that point, you're looking
at a full
replacement instead of being able to
repair things here and there. So,
and so you're looking at a couple
hundred,000. Yeah. Plus, and you have
the maintenance on the
wood to paint them this and that. Mhm.
Get up to them to do it. Okay. I'm just
trying to get a perspective of dollar
amounts. No, that's understandable. I
mean, that's why um the the state that
had us do all this research and stuff,
they made us um figure factor in how
often it would have to be painted, how
often things would have to be replaced.
And I think at the payback was about the
60 or 70 year mark um in terms of how
how often things had to be repaired
versus replaced and painted. Um so, and
the nice thing about the wood ones, once
you put them in, um you in theory can
just do repairs forever. You're not
looking at another full sale
replacement.
Okay, very good. Are you What? We have a
question here. I'm sorry, you didn't see
your hand. Uh, so do we have that cost
comparison between the different types
and the lifespan and the average over
those lifespans? You may. I gave it to
Car's predecessor a long time ago. Um,
it was probably two or three years ago
at this point. So, I'm not sure if you
still have it or not. If not, I can
certainly forward it to Carrie. Um,
so I was gonna say I don't know if you
if it would even be in your inbox or the
files that were left for you. I'm
looking to see if I have it access to it
quickly for you. Um,
I don't know that I have it with me. I'm
good with you just forwarding it. Okay.
While she's looking, perhaps you could
ask your question. Yeah. Um, are you
specifying a marine grade paint for the
windows? Um it is a it's a high
durability paint. I don't remember
exactly if it's considered marine grade
or not, but it's one that's been tested
with that type of wood and that type of
finish. So um again when we were working
with that that type of finish um one of
the wood window manufacturers um that we
are working with went off and did all
their own testing and research and
things and um talking to one of the main
p paint manufacturers to really kind of
boil down what works really well because
as you know um you know when once you
start factoring in access you don't want
to go with the cheap paint you want the
good paint. So yeah, the paint is not
where you cheap out on the process. So
yeah,
thank you. You're welcome. But will that
not be part of your specs for the build?
It will be. I just honestly don't
remember exactly which paint it is off
the top of my head. And then the next
question, I mean, we're we're
approaching spring. We're getting ready
for good weather. When will you have a
bid package ready to go out and how long
does that bid package take to takes to
work it through the cycle? So, we're
hoping to have the um drawings and plan
is, let's see, it's March 24th, probably
in about two weeks, two, three weeks. Um
and then once it is out, um bid periods
in Ohio are generally three weeks. So,
um and then after that, it's a matter of
um sitting down um with Carrie and her
team um making a recommendation and then
um going through your approval process.
Okay. Thank you. Yeah. Auditor Neville
had a question. Well, it's not so much a
question. And I want to kind of
enlighten um council for the existing
windows that are in the building. Um I
started with the city in
2005 and majority of the windows
including the ones that were in my
office. It took two to three people to
open and shut them. It was it's it's a
challenge. And then there was at the end
you heard the spring snapping and a lot
of the windows wouldn't open period. And
the the draft that was coming in you
could hold a piece of paper up currently
and it would move. So the current
windows and I'm not knowledge of what
type of windows are in there aren't very
efficient and they are very hard to
manage because they are very very heavy
windows and whatever's in those windows
now can't support the opening and
closing of the old ropes probably broke.
Um they're actually no they're aluminum
windows. They're not the original wood
ones and they um are more than like
likely on a block and tackle system.
Okay. So, so they're basically a spring
balance and once windows get to a
certain size, they they don't like
spring balances. Yeah. And that we've
had one of our windows when we raised
it, you heard the loudsp go off and then
we were very grateful we got it closed
and it was never to be opened again. So,
most of those windows currently are
tough to open and close in city hall.
Chairman Wolfinger, well, we have a
question. Okay. Over here. You couldn't
see her. I just I found the quote from
2023 that had both sets of windows in
it. Okay. And the aluminum windows were
$186,450 cheaper than the wood, which is
our 200, which is aluminum. I'd still
like to see the details with the
lifespan and the cost over time. Okay.
Cost for the inside. What was the cost
for the inside portion in that quote?
The inside portion? Well, the outside
portion in this quote because this again
is a really old. It was in the beginning
of 2023, February of 23. So, the inside
was
3.4 million
3,451,843, which we do know it's more
expensive now. The inside, you just said
the inside. Inside. Oh, sorry, that was
outside. My apologies. That was the
exterior. The
interior looks
like the interior was five basically 5.3
million but that did not include the
elevator or the public corridors or the
interior finish which would have added
another 1.1 million. So 6.4 four to add
the interior with the total project
budget for exterior interior at that
time being
12.6 million.
Yep.
Okay, we have a question. Question.
So, municipal court, that's a historic.
Do those windows even open? Because I
don't think do do they they're just a I
mean I don't even think are they
designed to open. Some of them do. Most
of them don't. Um the ones that do Oh,
sorry. Sorry about it again. Uh the ones
that do are likewise hard to open. Um
and they won't stay open. They just fall
back closed.
So, I mean, what what part of is it the
up two top floors that have the windows
that don't open? Because I I can I mean,
I was just talking to him. I'm like,
"Wait a minute. I don't think those
windows are just straight windows."
Yeah. None of the windows on the front
of the building open, period. It's all
of the windows to the, let's see, west,
south, and east faces of the building
that are in um you know, non-public
areas. They they open.
Okay. Okay. That's cheaper than windows
at open if we'd have something like that
in some of the windows at city hall. Um
generally yes. They they can be a little
um less expensive though not
significantly. So the hard thing is then
so this goes back to the same state
capital. Um they had a legislature that
decided u well the maintenance staff
decided they didn't want the windows to
open. The legislature decided they did
and passed a law requiring it. Um so
they went back and forth both both ways.
They're an interesting group.
Um, and what our ultimate recommendation
is, make the windows operable. If you're
concerned for security of people opening
them or opening them too far, you can
easily put basically a block of wood
that's screwed into the jam, pan it out
to match, that that way you can either
limit how much it opens or keep it from
opening entirely. But on the off chance
that, you know, for some reason you need
to be able to open that window, it is an
easy thing to reverse. Um, so that way,
you know, I always am a proponent of
operable windows. You know, what if your
power goes out? Some nice ventilation
would be nice. We're also coming upon
the time of year that being able to open
a window is a nice thing. Um, but yes,
you can make them so they're fixed. So
So it' be cheaper to do it the other
way. It is generally cheaper because my
thing about you talking about if I f
worried about somebody falling out of
the window, I'm not because if you're
dumb enough to hang out of a window and
fall out, that's on
you. You know, we're all adults here.
It's But uh I I think we need to I don't
know why that couldn't I mean be an
option, too. I mean, I don't know that
they have to open if I mean because I
see buildings all around. I mean, where
I'm in the hospital where I work, I
mean, our windows don't open. Mhm. I
mean, so if it's cheaper and I know this
historic thing, but I'm thinking of
dollar amounts, so I don't I don't know
why they have to actually necessarily
open.
Okay. Other questions from anybody? I
think didn't you say that that's law
that the legislature wrote it into law
that they in that particular state? Yes.
Pardon me. In that particular state, the
legislature wrote a law that was very
specific that they had the right to
determine by office which windows could
operate. Okay, that doesn't make any
sense either, but that's what they did
determined. So, and we then promptly
renovated the rest of the building. So,
no one was in the same office. So,
um looking at longterm um if you can
afford to make them operable, I would.
We can always limit it or close them
completely once they're in and done.
It's very expensive to go the other way.
So, okay. Thank you. Um, service safety
director. Um, did Eric show up yet? He
is not here yet. So, we asked the our uh
business building inspector, facilities
manager to show up. Uh, but he's on
these with the fire department. Yeah, he
went uh the facilities manager and the
fire chief went to go visit different
fire departments today to start looking
at layouts for potential firehouses,
what they like, what they didn't like,
and looking at some of the different um
firehouses that are in the in central
Ohio and to Dayton, I think, is actually
where Thank you. I just wanted to make
sure council wanted to hear from him
that we made the effort. U maybe if he
comes later on, I don't know how all of
that works in the rigorous session, but
u want that be clear. Uh, anything else
to present on this and we'll move on. If
not, let you get back to Columbus.
Thanks. Um, that's all everything I
have. I I'm excited that you're looking
at restoring the city hall. You do have
a one of the most beautiful city halls.
It's um surprisingly large and u
monumental for the size of the city. And
most people keep calling it a courthouse
or county courthouse, but um it's going
to be a great building and um it already
is a great building. It would be
exciting to see it all fixed up and
something for the community to gather
around. So, we appreciate you being
here. You might not have been there at
the time, but the decorative arts
building, I was very much involved with
that project. Oh, nice. Yeah. Back in
the day as well done. Thank you. So, we
should be very proud of it. Thank you.
Thanks. Then, um, nothing else. I will I
would I think it would be good to hear
from the historic lure commission
president who's here and chairman, I
should say. uh advising us on the what
their rule is set by this council.
There's legislation that applies to this
decision too and I think you should hear
from him if Brian if you would come up
and introduce yourself and explain your
role on the HLC. Yeah, absolutely.
Thanks, Mayor McDaniel. Uh good evening.
My name is Brian Rev. the chair of the
historic Langster Commission and I will
try to keep this brief because I know
you have a lot to get to but uh Mayor
McDaniel asked me to kind of talk
briefly about our process after the
subject matter expert came up to talk
about the windows. Um so the historic
Langster Commission was originally
established in 1977. The purpose of that
was to ensure that the character of the
city's historic properties is taken into
account in rehabilitation, remodeling or
new construction work. Um and we are
guided from a statutory perspective from
Langster codified ordinance chapter
1327. And uh we then use what are known
as the historic Langster design
guidelines which are based on the
secretary of the interior standards for
rehabilitation um to recommend
appropriate treatment of historic
buildings. These are all available on
our website. If any individual wants
more information, I'd be happy to talk
offline um or send you the link to where
these are. But um in these guidelines
and in looking at the recommendation for
appropriate treatment um the guidelines
always begin with the most conservative
treatment and then move towards other
treatments that may or may not be
warranted. Um they additionally give
weight to certain considerations when
looking at the structure. Uh for example
a primary versus secondary facade. So
there may be differences in what is
allowable on the street facing facade
versus what is allowable on the rear
alley facade. Um and another thing that
they look at is whether a building is
specifically contributing to the
historic district or not. Um looking at
the historic designation for the
different districts that we have where
the design guidelines are applicable.
They look at contributing buildings,
ones that are considered unique and
contributing in and of themselves, which
city hall is. And they look at other
buildings, uh, more typically less
ornate buildings or homes or things that
may be on the border more towards the
exterior boundaries of the district. So,
being at the intersection that it's at
and being what it is, the 1897 city
hall, it is both a contributing
building. Um it's kind of the cream of
the crop under our standards that we
look at. Um to discuss windows
specifically um I've just taken some
guidelines uh some quotes from the
guidelines. The way it generally works
in the guidelines it's divided into
sections. It talks about roofs, talks
about siding, talks about awnings, talks
about windows etc. It discusses from a
historic perspective how those fit into
the envelope of historic structure and
then it has recommendations and those
are the guidelines that both we as a
historic langster commission use but
also what we point individuals that are
coming before us for certificate of
appropriateness to look at as they step
through what is and is not permissible.
Uh the guidelines say windows contribute
to a building's character in a
significant way. They help to define its
character. It goes on to say they
enhance character and define style. In
the recommendations, it says that the
first step again getting back to this
most conservative method is to maintain
and repair to preserve what is already
there. If that's not possible, then it
goes to selective replacement where one
would replace only those elements of a
feature that are damaged and would do so
in a like forlike manner. So if you're
have a window that is damaged for
example, you would rebuild and replace
the the lower sash, the upper sash. You
would repair the meeting rail or
something of that window with like for
like. It also directs to retain historic
glass when appropriate or when possible.
Um if you get into the position of new
windows, it says new windows should
match originally as or the original,
excuse me, as closely as possible in
material, size, profile, and appearance.
Um, replacement windows should match
historic windows in all of the details
and materials. And it says, example,
wood for wood. Um, if you're not able to
do that again as you step through
repairing and maintaining what is there,
replacing a portion of what is there,
um, and you move to replacing like for
like, the next step is what's called
using substitute material. And we have a
stepby-step guideline for what we look
at for what we can do on that. Some of
those recommendations are substitute
materials are generally not recommended
in the historic Lancaster district
unless the following circumstances
apply. The building is non-contributing
to the district or not a listed property
or the building is contributing to the
district or listed property but the
substitute material will be used only on
a secondary elevation or feature that is
not highly v visible or the materials
proposed for new construction including
new construction and additions. So
again, I just wanted to quickly walk
through being respectful of the time
that's already been um spent on this and
give you an idea of what the guidelines
that we are held to as a historic
Langster Commission discuss with respect
to materials and then a little bit with
respect to windows. I'd entertain any
questions and like I said in the
interest of time, I'd be happy to talk
or or share links outside of this
meeting as well. Thank Thank you very
much. Questions? Go ahead. Um thank you
for that information. it just for my
understanding so I have a comparison um
would the Georgian or the Sherman
buildings be con be considered
contributing buildings also I believe
they both are okay thank you absolutely
any architectural questions
very good thank you very much appreciate
you taking the time
Law Director Hall, did you want to say
anything or not? Or um just to
Councilwoman Kite's last point, um City
Hall is a listed building. It's on the
National Register of Historic Places, so
it's contributing and it's listed both
technically. Thank you. Thank you. Good.
Thank
you. I hear no other comments or hands
raised. So, I'm going to return to the
normal agenda of the finance committee.
uh resolutions. First resolution is
temporary resolution
28-25, a resolution to authorize the
mayor to enter into a contract with the
Fairfield County General Health District
for public health services. This is
coming from administrating services
committee and Councilman Luckenberg. Uh
thank you.
the uh Lancaster doesn't have a health
department and it has contracted for
years with the Fairfield County Health
Department to provide those services for
Lancaster and uh that this legislation
before us is the same contract they've
used year after year with the Fairfield
County Health Department. It only
represents a 2% increase over last
year's contract. So, okay,
questions. Um, we didn't we not at one
time have multiple year contracts versus
one year? Not to my knowledge, but
possibly the law director can speak to
that. Sorry. Yes. Um, we did at one
point have uh multiple year contracts,
but I believe that was before the
current um the
current commissioner, thank you.
Couldn't think of the word. Yes. uh
before he came on. Y that's because
someone asked me that and I guess I'm
old because I do remember that. Sorry
about that. Any other questions and I
guess I'm your second. Three readings
and three readings. Thank you. Moving
on. Temporary resolution
29-25, a resolution to appropriate from
the unencumbered balance and amend
certificate of appropriation with the
county auditor in the temper top tiff
fund
306 coming from finance and I will have
three readings and uh council nails
you'll be the second on that. Yes. and I
will turn it over to Auditor Nettles if
you have anything you wish to add. Um,
this is just the carryover cash that um
I forgot to budget for um in this year's
budget and uh we've been working on the
law director's been working on with the
Timbertop and the companies. So, I need
to get that appropriated. So, when we
need to make payment, um I'll have that
budgeted to do so.
Thank you. Is that also a factor of the
county auditor not releasing the numbers
in time to fit into our budget? No, it
was just more of I guess and I thought
we were going to do a payout last year.
So, I assumed I made an assumption that
we would pay it out. That didn't occur.
So, I missed that in that budget
timeline. So, it was just kind of a
miscommunication and I just noticed that
it wasn't budgeted. So, I needed to get
that budgeted. Thank you very much. No
other questions, comments. Temporary
resolution
30-25, a resolution of the city of
Lanster to approve the Fairfield County
E9-1-1, otherwise 911 final plan coming
from the safety committee and uh
Councilman Bisch. Uh thank you, Mr.
Chair. I just want to share that council
member Tiner is going to be my second on
this legislation. Uh and to dive in
deeper here into this legislation, I'll
turn it over to Service Safety Director
Woody.
I will actually defer to Chief Snyder. I
think he's out in the audience. He's a
little more familiar with this than I
am, so I will let him speak to this.
Actually, Chief, I'll be happy to take
it because it's something that the mayor
sits on this committee and uh although
the chief would be capable of answering
these questions, this is a state
requirement. the state re uh reworked
the uh code uh for 911 plans. Fairfield
counties was 30 years old. And so the
county commissioners, the mayor of the
largest city, uh township trustee from
the largest township and a couple other
people were involved in this committee.
And then one of the things we have to do
is review the plan itself operationally,
which the chief and our communication
tech supervisor participated in that.
but also how we divide the 911 tariff
money. Uh so every time you uh pay your
cell bill, you're paying a 911 tariff
with that cell phone bill. So there is a
portion of that money comes back to the
city of Lanster, Fairfield County, uh
Picker and Police Department, and it's
divided based on call volume. So we sat
down uh we all agreed with the plan and
this was voted on as required by the
revised code. So, the plan's been
approved by the county 911 committee and
it must be in order to be final it needs
to be approved by the legislative
authority of each jurisdiction involved.
Thank you. Very thorough.
Uh moving on, no questions. Temporary uh
or move to ordinances. Temporary
ordinance
19-25. An ordinance for the issuance and
sale of notes in the maximum principal
amount of $7 million in anticipation of
the issuance of bonds for the purpose of
paying the cost of the renovation and
rehabilit rehabilitation I'm sorry of
the city hall building and otherwise
improving the site thereafter therefore
uh together with all necessary purchases
therefore thereto and declaring an
emergency coming from finance
uh Uh, Councilman Sulli will be my
second. We will have three readings.
Um, would you like to explain that a
little bit or I can kind of go through
it? This is the um debt ordinance giving
permission to go out for bid and uh no,
she's going out for bid but to to uh
private place a note um for the city to
pay for these renovations. Um, we did a
not to exceed seven million not knowing
the bid. The engineers estimate wasn't
that high, but we kind of bumped it up.
We'll only borrow what we need, but
we're hoping that that covers what bids
will come back. So, that's kind of we're
hinging on those bids, but yes, this can
go three readings and it's um again the
going out to get the debt for the
courthouse or city hall.
And a bit of history, uh, we went
through a similar program with the
municipal court building down the street
and we ended up with a lot of cost
overruns and things that just a
100-year-old plus building gets into
situations. You can't really tell until
you get into it. So that's why you have
a little spread there. Uh we will be
back into the finance committee to do
permanent financing next year, probably
May time frame if it's all works out.
And that uh may or may not be the $7
million. Uh we might have to come back
to council to approve an override if
necessary depending what we we find in
this particular building. Um uh because
we ended up with tons of overrides,
overruns back in uh 8 years
ago. No other questions. I will move
forward to excuse me, temporary
ordinance 20-25, an ordinance to accept
the annexation of 5.08 plus or minus
acres in Pleasant Township and to
declare an emergency. coming from the
economic development committee. Uh
Councilman
H. I'm
sorry. This is just the final approval
of the annexation of the five acres out
in Pleasant Township.
Um and it can go three readings. And
Councilwoman Crates is my second. Okay.
Very good. And law director Hall, did
you have any comments you wish to make?
Nope. She hit the nail on the head.
Thank you. Very good. Thank you. Um, no
other questions. Thank you. Temporary
ordinance 21-25, an ordinance to amend
the zoning map subject to passage of the
annexation of
5.08 plus or minus acres in Pleasant
Township and declared an emergency. Also
coming from Economic Development
Committee, uh, Councilman Hoop. Um yeah,
this is the
same five acres that the zoning is going
to be advanced
manufacturing
and councilman wing is going to be my
second three readings. Three
readings questions. Thank you.
And we have temporary ordinance
22-25, an ordinance to amend section
1339.13 of the codified ordinances of
the city of Lancaster entitled in
quotation wireless
telecommunications coming from code
enforcement and zoning committee. Uh
Councilman Luckenberg. Yes. Thank you,
Chairman Wolfinger. Um, this uh
particular ordinance was written in 2002
and it required all telecommunication
towers to submit all owners of
telecommunication towers to submit an
annual maintenance report and a $500
fee. Since then, the FCC has taken over
responsibility for uh regulatory and and
reporting items like this and uh so
we're just simply removing that from the
ordinances with this legislation makes a
lot of
sense and
Councilman Hoop is your three. Three
readings. Thank you. U that concludes
all the resolutions and ordinances
coming before first reading tonight at
council. Uh we'll move to other
discussion items and departmental
updates. Does anybody department head
would like to
Okay. Thank you, Chairman Wolfinger. I
did want to let everyone know that I
will have legislation uh before you at
our next meeting. So, if you all recall
last year, we did the NOPC energy grant
where we took around $30,000 to start
replacing our lighting in some of our
city-owned buildings. And we did
legislation last year. I budgeted for
it. So, it's already budgeted in our
budget this year. And I thought that
since it was budgeted, I could use that
resolution to submit to NOPEC to get
reimbursed. However, they want specific
legislation
um to submit to get our reimbursement
for that. So, I will have that to you at
our next meeting to request
reimbursement. Um, we have already spent
the funds. It's uh around
$31,000. Uh, we replaced most of the
lighting in city hall to make it energy
efficient with this grant money, but in
order for them to reimburse us, we will
have to do legislation. So, it can go
three readings. However, uh, if we could
go two readings, that would be even
better so that I can submit for
reimbursement. And that was 31,000.
Correct.
And I believe it's U acronym is N O E
PC. N O P E C. Yes. PC. Thank
you. And we have someone who wants to
speak.
Hi. Is this on? Okay. It doesn't sound
like it to me. Um, I'm going to bring
some legislation in two weeks um for you
guys to review about uh participating in
a housing study for Lancaster. The
county is initiating it, but I've been
in all the meetings where we're talking
uh to the consultant as to what kind of
information we want to see. Um, and what
it's going to do is tell us if we have
enough housing, if we don't have enough
housing, and give us a great um,
overview of what types of housing we
have um, and talking about growth and
and what we need to do or not do um, to
create a balanced housing market. And
another uh portion that's really
important to us is um being able to
provide some information about how to um
essentially keep the city and the county
and the schools whole as we continue to
develop. So I'll come back in two weeks
and um and and present it all to you
guys. I have a question
actually. Can you tell me by chance
ballpark how many housing studies have
we had? It seems like we're having a
study for this, a study for that,
constantly spending money on this and
then nothing ever happens. I just kind
of wonder, can you do a like look into
that for me? Sure. You know, in the last
three years, I know Lancaster hasn't
done any um while I'm here. But I you
might also be thinking about the
comprehensive plan that Fairfield County
just did, which the city did not part um
the city participated, but the city did
not participate financially. So they did
a a h they did a an overview
comprehensive study on the whole county.
Well, and I know we did like the Cedar
Hill thing and we've done all that and
we've done so it seems like there's
always something out there. Somebody's
there's a committee for this or a
committee for that. And I mean clearly
we need affordable housing and I mean I
I don't know why I I don't know. Just
something we need and we just keep kind
of just saying oh we're going to do this
we're going to do that. we're gonna
check into this and nothing ever
happens.
Yeah. Well, I I would suggest that we've
got a lot of new housing starts and a
lot of but a lot of stuff in in the air
and but but you know the one thing the
one people the the guy that came I
remember was it last year you know you
had to make I don't know it was n going
to be like $950 for a a place to stay.
But if you got you had more money, then
it was going to cost more. And and it
was just like, you know, nobody can get
ahead because, you know, you try to get
that second job and oh no, you make too
much money, so you're going to have to
pay more and to to live here. It's just,
you know, Yeah. I mean, we need to do
something here. Yeah. So, in terms of
affordable housing, the South Ewing
development that we just had the
groundbreaking for is going to provide
219 units at 30 to 80% of AMI. So that
will be very uh that'll be that'll be
very effective. WODA is under
construction already for 40 um
affordable units on Cells Road. We're
working with another project over on Edy
Road. Um and I hope I'm not forgetting
anything else. And then our market rate
projects all have a component of
affordability. So it's been um at least
20% are below AMI, below market rate.
So, we are certainly trying to um
address that issue, but we also want to
make sure are we building too much? Are
we because I know some people may feel
like we're building a lot because it's
just been this rush all of a sudden we
have all these housing projects. So, you
know, this will tell us if we have
enough or not enough. And then when it
comes to um what we don't have enough
of, then we can really be intentional
and and attract the developers. um that
are going to create the products that we
need and and the look that we need too.
Yeah. Well, I think we have a lot really
right now. It's just people can't afford
it. That's the problem. Yeah. So, and is
this a county? I'm sorry. Are you
finished? Oh, yeah. Um this is a
countywide study. Yes. They're going to
cover the unincorporated areas of the
county and Lancaster, but not Pickerton
or Canal or at this time. From what I
understand, they do not want to
participate. I think Canal just did a
housing study. I don't know what
Pickerington's reasoning was. They were
they talked to Rick Zack, our county
economic development director. And also
about the Cedar Hill study, wasn't that
all done internally with um um No, no,
just kidding. No, but I think I think
we're confusing the um the zoning code
updates that were done. Um and the Cedar
Hill housing or the Cedar Hill
neighborhood area plan was a part of
that. Um, and that was specifically
because Morpsy had asked that the city
or recommended to the city that we look
at uh making that corridor into town a
little more appealing. Right. I remember
that. And so that was all part that came
as a result of the zoning code update,
the the comprehensive coning zoning code
that was changed in order to allow more
density because the problem was, you
know, we only have so much space, right?
You also talked about building an
apartment complex or something around
that area too. That was I don't recall
that. I apologize. I can tell you the
last development plan that the city had,
comprehensive development plan was from
1991. Um it's it's comic sans sah font
if you ever want to read it. It's really
Well, but I'm I'm just saying I do
remember there was there was talk also
because because people were sent this
stuff and and they were kind of I would
guess it was a result of all of that
that comprehensive zoning outlook, but
that that really didn't do anything in
terms of a specific housing study
unfortunately.
Sorry. And the cost of the study
Lancaster share $10,000 from the city,
10,000 from the port
and we identified funding source for
that. We are working on that. Okay.
Thank you. Thank you. FYI, the county's
portion is 26,000 at this point. It is.
Yeah. Right. Yeah. So, it's a total
36,000. It's actually a total total of
73,000 for the whole study. And I'll
I'll be sure to Yeah, if you if you can
break that in in the legislation
somewhere, right? I like to know where
the money's Yeah. coming from and where
it's going. And um Oh, there was one
other thing I was going to say and it
slipped my mind. I'll remember it when I
sit down. I'll just come back up. You
can do it anytime you want. Thank you.
Any other questions of council? Mr.
Chairman, I just want to uh for uh
everyone, LDG has announced their
starting rent on uh South Eing Street is
723 a month. that is a one-bedroom.
That's their starting point. Uh that's
more affordable than what we've seen uh
in some of the uh market rate projects
Becky referred to. There is a
significant effort to bring affordable
housing and that's what LDG is building
and that's what WOA Cooper is building.
These other ones are market rate.
Essentially, if you want to be there,
you pay the market rate and it's rather
expensive, but all of them are full.
So there's a need for that too is my
point. There's a need for all of it. The
housing study will help us understand
what we have at each level.
Affordability and market
rate, single family homes, where should
they be, how many? So we kind of need
some guidance that, you know, we all
think we need this or we think we need
that or we think we may not need this or
we may not need that. The purpose of the
study is to try to refine that and
actually have
informed answers as to what we might
need and what we can attract at that
point going forward. So, we're working
on all of it. And the study will
indicate viable sites. We're starting to
run out of land, aren't we? Yeah, we are
starting to run out of land. Um, that's
why I mean the city's been really
generous in allowing annexations where
they've been needed. So, yeah, we are
running out of land. So, we'll might be
looking at more annexation in the
future. I certainly don't want to don't
want to assume that. Um, but it could
happen. Okay. Yeah. Thank you,
Chief. You haven't been up here for a
while. Do you want to talk?
Okay. Very good. I assume there's no
other uh departmental update. Oh, you
have one. I knew there's going to be a
third one. Sorry, Chairman Wolfinger.
Um, back on housing real quick. I just
wanted to say if any of you have
received a call from any of your
constituents regarding the notices that
the city sent out for a public hearing.
Um, they were kind of confusing and I
apologize for that in advance. Bricker
actually had to write them up and
they're written um to match what the
codified ordinance requires. Um, but I
want to be very clear. So, these went
out to folks over off of independence
declaration in that neighborhood. Um,
we're talking about the Powers Run Tiff
incentive districts. So, we had to let
everybody know that their properties or
the properties in the actual district
are going to be developed. Um, and so
all of the people around got notice as
well, but nothing will change with
regard to any of their houses. The the
letter did make that very clear. There
will be no increase to property tax. Um,
there will be no change in zoning.
Nothing changes with regard to those
properties. The only properties that
will potentially have some impact on
them are those that are owned by the
developer and the developer has already
consented. Um, you know, he's giving us
an NCA and we're giving him a tiff. So,
it's only the developer properties that
are going to be affected. So, if anybody
gets a question or or you know something
that they can't answer, please feel free
to send that my way. Um, the mayor's
office is sending everybody to me and so
far I've been able to to answer all of
the questions. I'm sure somebody can
come up with one that I can't, but um,
if you get one, just feel free to send
them to send them my way. And also, the
public hearing will be April 21st at
6:30 here in council
chambers if anybody wants to attend.
Okay. Thank you.
And thank you. I'm gonna move real quick
to depart um meeting prep by President
Porter. For tonight's meeting, we have
10 resolutions on the agenda and seven
ordinances. No special presentations.
Thank you very much. Uh we've already
covered the other items. Uh there's no
need for executive session. So I would
entertain a motion
to close our meeting. Motion. Second.
All those in favor? I I so moved. We are
adjourned and it is
6:55. Just turned.
The regular meeting for Lancaster City
Council will convene at 7:05.
The Frankie Smith Funeral Home and
Crematory in Lancaster and the Johnson
Smith Funeral Home in Baltimore have a
long and wonderful history of serving
our community. Feel free to give us a
call at
74-653652. Stop in and see us at either
of our two locations, 405 North Columbus
Street in Lancaster and 207 South Main
Street in Baltimore. Respect for
tradition, regard for change.
Hi, I'm David Ole with the Fairfield
County Board of Developmental
Disabilities. As many of you know, we're
here to help bring about a vibrant
community where people lead lives of
greater independence and make meaningful
contributions. We're truly blessed to
have local supporters like Buckeye
Toyota and Buckeye Honda to once again
make a donation with each car sold this
month through the Buckeye Cares program.
Please support the generous local
business that helps reinforce our
community. And just like me, you'll be
saying, "That's how I buckeye.
[Music]
you're able join me in a moment of
prayer. God, grant us the serenity to
accept the things that we cannot change,
the courage to change the things we can,
and finally, the wisdom to know the
difference. I now call to order the
March 24th, 2025 Lancaster City Council
meeting. Please join me in the pledge of
allegiance. I pledge algiance to the
flag of the United States of America and
to the republic for which it stands. One
nation under God, indivisible, with
liberty and justice for all.
Please call the role. Mr. Als here. Mr.
Bisjack here. Mrs. K here. Mrs. Hoop
here. Mr. Lenberg here. Mr. Skunover
here, Mr. Sullie here, Miss Teener here,
Mr. Wing here, and Mr. Wolfinger here.
Please let the record reflect that all
10 members of Lancaster City Council are
present. We'll now move to the reading
and disposing of the journal. I have
regular meeting minutes dated March
10th, 2025.
Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
to receive and file the journal. Second.
We have a motion and a second to receive
and file the journal. All those in
favor, please signify by saying I. I. I.
All those opposed, same sign. Please
make sure that everybody's mics are on
and that we're speaking in them just for
purposes of um recording. Thank you. Um
we now move to the reports of city
officials. I have email dated March
17th, 2025 regarding 2026 health
department contract submitted by mayor
executive assistant Shannon Shashultz.
Email dated March 18, 2025 regarding
special park board meeting submitted by
Park Superintendent Steve Gayfield.
Email dated March 20th, 2025 regarding
Lancaster Fire Department 2024 annual
report submitted by Fire Chief Slade
Schultz. Email dated March 20th, 2025
regarding community conver or
conversation submitted by city planner
um Cheline Carter. email. And finally,
email dated March 20th, 2025 regarding
Fairfolk County E911 plan approval
submitted by law director Stephanie
Hall.
Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
to receive and file the reports of city
officials. Second. We have a motion, a
second to receive and file the reports
of city officials. All those in favor,
please signify by saying I. I. All those
opposed, same sign. Communications. I
have email dated March 17, 2025
regarding public records request for
zoning verification on 111 South
Memorial Drive, Lancaster. Submitted by
Cheryl King with SBRE, Assessment and
Consulting Services. Email dated March
22nd, 2025 regarding speaking on a topic
at council meetings um submitted by Barb
Summers. email dated March 20th, 2020
um regarding an email chain from Joe
Bisjack on March 22nd public meeting
submitted by Talia
Basari. And that's the item.
Mr. President, like to make a motion to
receive and file the communications.
Second. Have a motion, a second to
receive and file the communications. All
those in favor signify by saying I. I.
All those opposed, same sign. We have no
special presentations or awards this
evening. We have no petitions or
memorials. We now have reached the point
in the agenda that we have permission of
voters and taxpayers to address council.
If you so choose, please move to the
podium. Sign in with your name and
address on the sheet. Give your name and
address. You're limited to three
minutes. Thank you. Thank you. I had a
question about the bond for the $7
million. Do we know the interest rate?
Sir, this is not a time to ask questions
to council. Um, you are here to address
council with any public concerns or
anything like that. It's not a question
and answer session. And we do need you
to identify yourself and give your name
and address the board. All right. Well,
yeah, if you guys know the answer to
that, that'd be great for the life of
the bond, the length of the bond, and
the interest rate on that, that would be
fantastic.
Thank you. Anybody else wish to address
council this
evening hearing? None. Did this person
sign in or introduce themselves? He said
he signed in. He did. Yeah, he came up
during the break. I just didn't
introduce himself.
Um, if there are no others, we thank you
for coming this evening and your
attendance at the meeting. Thank you.
Reports of standing committees. A
finance committee meeting minutes dated
March 10th, 2025 submitted by Mr.
Wolfinger. Water water pollution control
committee agenda dated March 12th, 2025
submitted by Mr. Wing. Law committee
agenda dated March 14th, 2025 submitted
by Miss
Kites. Public works committee agenda
dated March 14th, 2025, submitted by
Miss Tiner. Finance Committee agenda
dated March 22nd, 2025 submitted by Mr.
Wolfinger. Service committee meeting
minutes dated March 23rd, 2025,
submitted by Mr. Als.
Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
to receive and file the reports of
standing committees. Second. We have a
motion and second to receive and file
the reports of standing committees. All
those in favor, please signify by saying
I. I. All those opposed, same sign.
Reports of special committees. There are
no reports. We have no public hearings
scheduled for this evening. We will now
move to the reading of resolutions.
Beginning with the third reading of
resolutions. Uh first temporary
resolution 20-25.
A resolution to authorize the service
safety director to dispense with
competitive bidding in to a contract
with Montrose Ford for the purchase of
four police vehicles for the use by the
Lancaster Police Department. This is
through safety committee, Mr. Bisjack
and Miss Tamer. Council member Bisjack.
Thank you, Mr. President. I move that
council pass engross and enter upon the
written record temporary resolution
20-25. Second. We have a motion second.
pass and gross and enter upon the
written record temporary resolution
20-25. Discussion, Council Member
Bisjack. Uh, thank you, Mr. President.
Once again, this is just allowing the
safety service director to uh enter into
a contract with Montrose Ford for the
purchase of four police vehicles. Thank
you. Any further
discussion? Hearing none, please call
the role. Mr. Als, yes. Mr. Bisjack,
yes. Mrs. Kes, yes. Mrs. Hoop, yes. Mrs.
L. Mr. L. Yes. Mr. Skunover. Yes. Mr.
Sully, yes. Miss Tiner, yes. Mr. Wing,
yes. And Mr. Wolfinger, yes. Temporary
resolution 20-25 passes 10 to zero.
Temporary resolution 21-25,
a resolution to appropriate from the
unencumbered balance and to amend the
certificate with the county auditor in
the general
fund. This is through safety committee,
Mr. Bisjack and Mr. Sully. Council
member Bisjack. Thank you, Mr.
President. And I move that council pass
it and engross upon the written record
temporary resolution 21-25.
Second. We have a motion and second to
pass and grow and enter upon the written
record temporary resolution
21-25. Discussion. Council member
Bisjack. Thank you, Mr. President. Once
again, this is just appropriating
$200,000 for the HVAC system that we're
installing in the police department. Uh
this is $200,000 that was not spent last
fiscal year, but will be spent this
fiscal year. So, this is not new
additional money uh going into the
project. That's all. Thank you. Any
further discussion? Hearing none, please
call the role. Mr. Als, yes. Mr.
Bisjack, yes. Mrs. Kites, yes. Mrs. H,
yes. Mr. Luckenberg, yes. Mr. Scoover,
yes. Mr. Sullie, yes. Miss Tiner, yes.
Mr. Wing, yes. And Mr. Wolfinger? Yes.
Temporary resolution 21-25 passes 10 to
zero. Temporary resolution 23-25.
A resolution to appropriate from the
unencumbered balance in the cemetery
perpetual care fund
8034. Complete a fund transfer, increase
receipts and appropriations in the
cemetery fund
20007 and amend the certificate of other
sources and appropriations with the
county auditor. This is through public
works committee, Miss Tiner and Mr.
Luckenberg. Council member Tiner. Mr.
President, I'd like to make a motion
that council pass and gross and enter
upon the written record uh temporary
resolution 2325.
Second. We have a motion and a second to
pass and gross and enter upon the
written record temporary resolution
2325. Any discussion? Council member
Tiner. Um Tim Deetsz had been here
before. It's just uh regarding the funds
of the um cemetery. Thank you. Any
further discussion?
Hearing none, please call the role. Mr.
Mr. Als, yes. Mr. Bisjack, yes. Mrs.
Kit, yes. Mrs. Hoop, yes. Mr. Luenberg,
yes. Mr. Skunover, yes. Mr. Sully, yes.
Miss Tiner, yes. Mr. Wing, yes. And Mr.
Wolfinger, yes. Resolution
23-25 passes 10 to zero. Temporary
resolution 24-25.
A resolution to authorize the service
safety director to dispense with
competitive biddy for a sole source
provider for corrosion inhibitors. This
is through water water pollution
committee. Mr. Wing and Miss Tiner.
Council member Wing. Uh yes, Mr.
President. I move that council pass and
gross and enter upon the written record
temporary resolution 24-25.
Second. We have a motion and second to
pass and gross and enter upon the
written record temporary resolution
24-25. Any discussion? Council member
Wink. Uh yes. Briefly, uh this declares
Caris Corporation uh the source the soul
source corrosion emitter. Um the water
department has used this since uh 1996
and it's the only company that can
provide what we need in bulk supply.
Thank you. Any further discussion?
Hearing none, please call the role. Mr.
Als, yes. Mr. Bisch, yes. Mrs. K, yes.
Mrs. Hoop, yes. Mr. Luxenberg, yes. Mr.
Skoonver, yes. Mr. Sullie, yes. Miss
Ter, yes. Mr. Wing, yes. And Mr.
Wolfinger? Yes. Temporary resolution
24-25 passes 10 to zero. Temporary
resolution 25-25,
a resolution to authorize the service
safety director to advertise for bids
and enter into a contract for the city
hall renovation project. This is through
finance committee, Mr. Wolfinger and Mr.
Sully. Council member Wolfinger. Thank
you, Mr. President. I'd like to make a
motion that council pass and gross and
enter upon the written record temporary
resolution 25-25.
Council member saw second.
We have a motion and a second to pass a
gross enter upon the written record
temporary resolution
25-25. Any discussion? Council member
Wolfinger. Well, I'll be very brief with
the discussion. We've we've certainly
talked a lot about it and the finance
committee and and actually this is the
the renovation of city hall uh at $7
million and uh that's the estimated cost
at this point in time. that this gives
the authority for the service safety
director to take it out for bid. Any
further discussion?
Hearing none, please call the role. Mr.
Als, yes. Mr. Visjack, yes. Mrs. Kra,
no.
Mr. Luenberg,
yes. I'm sorry. Mrs. Hoop, yes. Mr.
Skoover, yes. Mr. Sullie, yes. Miss Ter,
no.
Mr. Mr. Wing. Yes. And Mr. Wolfinger.
Yes.
Temporary resolution
25-25 passes 82.
[Music]
We will now move to the second reading
of resolutions beginning with temporary
resolution 26-25.
A resolution authorizing the Lancaster
Tree Commission to apply for the Ohio
Department of Natural Resources Urban
Forestry Grant and to declare an
emergency. This is through service
committee, Mr. Als and Mr. Wing.
Council member Als. Yes, Mr. President.
I move that council suspend its rules
and wave the third reading of temporary
resolution 26-25.
Second. We have a motion and second to
suspend the rules and wave the third
reading of temporary resolution
2625. Any discussion on the motion to
suspend?
Please call the role. Mr. Als, yes. Mr.
Bisjack, yes. Mrs. Kates, yes. Mrs.
Hoop, yes. Mr. Luenberg, yes. Mr.
Skunover, yes. Mr. Sully, yes. Miss
Tiner, yes. Mr. Wing, yes. And Mr.
Wolfinger, yes. Motion to suspend
carries 10 to zero. Council member Als.
Mr. President, I move that we pass and
engross and enter upon the written
record resolution temporarily number
2625.
Second. We have a motion and second to
pass engross and enter upon the written
record temporary resolution 2625. Any
discussion? Council member Als. Yes. My
wife says that I'm too serious in these
meetings. So tonight, because we're
discussing resolution 2625, which has to
do with the tree
commission, I work
I am a tree hugger. Proud. Thank you.
Tree hugger. Thank you. Thank you for
that discussion. Any further discussion
from council members? Hearing none,
please call the role. Mr. Als, yes. Mr.
Bisjack, yes. Mrs. Kra, yes. Mrs. Hoop,
yes. Mr. Lenberg, yes. Mr. Scoover, yes.
Mr. Sully, yes. Miss Tiner,
yes.
Mr. Wing. Yes. And Mr. Wolfinger. Yes.
Temporary resolution
2625 passes 10 to zero. Temporary
resolution 2725. A resolution
authorizing the city law director's
office to apply for the violence or
violence against women act grant. This
is through law committee. Mrs. Kates and
Mr. Bisjack. Council member Kates.
Second of three readings. Second of
three readings on temporary resolution
2725. We now move to the first reading
of resolutions beginning with temporary
resolution 2825.
A resolution to authorize the mayor to
enter into a contract with the Fairfield
County General Health District for
public health services. This is through
administrative services committee. Mr.
Luckenberg and Mr. Wolfinger. Council
member Luckenberg. First of three
readings. First of three readings on
temporary resolution 2825. Temporary
resolution 2925.
A resolution to appropriate from the
unencumbered balance and amend the
certificate of appropriations for the
county auditor and the timber top tiff
fund
3060. This is through finance committee
Mr. Wolfinger and Mr. Alles. Council
member Wolfinger. There'll be the first
of three readings. First of three
readings on temporary resolution 2925.
Temporary resolution 30-25.
Aition of the city of Lancaster to
approve the Fairfield County
E911 final plan. This is through safety
committee. Mr. Bisjack and Miss Tiner.
Council member Bisjack. Thank you, Mr.
President. This will be the first of
three readings. First of three readings
on temporary resolution
30-25. No further reading of
resolutions. We'll move to the reading
of ordinances. We have no third readings
this evening of ordinances. Second
reading of ordinances. We begin with
temporary ordinance 1525,
an ordinance to amend permanent
ordinance
55-24, also known as the parks and
recreation pay ordinance, and to declare
an emergency. This is through service
committee. U Mr. Als and Mrs. Hoop,
Council Member Als. Uh, second of three
readings. Second of three readings on
temporary ordinance 1525. Do we have a
t-shirt for that one? No. Okay.
Um, temporary temporary ordinance 1625,
an ordinance authorizing the mayor to
grant 10 permanent supplemental
easements to the Ohio Power Company
necessary for the construction and
maintenance of the electric facilities
and to declare an emergency. This is
through law committee. Um, Mrs. Kates
and Mr. Wolfinger. Council member Kates.
Second of three. Second of three
readings on temporary ordinance 1625.
Temporary Ordinance 18-25,
an ordinance authorizing the mayor to
accept an amended deed of the permanent
easement for the underground utility
facilities and to declare an emergency.
This is through the law committee, Mrs.
Kates and Mr. Wolfinger. Council member
Kates. Yes. Thank you, Mr. President. I
would like to make a motion that council
suspend its rules and wave the wave the
third reading of ordinance temporarily
numbered 18-25.
Second. We have a motion and a second to
suspend the rules and wave the third
reading of temporary ordinance
18-25. Is there any uh discussion?
Council member Kits. Yes, just briefly.
Um this is for uh to allow the city to
accept an amendment to a 2019 easement
uh where we're running city services to
residential development property out on
country club and the properties for sale
and that's why we're asking for
suspension. Thank you. Okay. Any further
discussion on the motion to
suspend? Hearing none, please call the
role. Mr. Als, yes. Mr. Bischack, yes.
Mrs. Craig, yes. Mrs. Hoop, yes. Mr.
Lockenberg, yes. Mr. Skunover, yes. Mr.
Sullie, yes. Miss Teener, yes. Mr. Wing,
yes. And Mr. Wolfinger, yes. Motion to
suspend the rules and wave the third
reading of temporary ordinance
18-25. Uh, passes 10 to zero. Council
member Kits. Yes. Thank you, Mr.
President. I would like to make a motion
that council pass and gross and enter
upon the written record ordinance
temporarily numbered 18-25.
Second. We have a motion in second to
pass and gross and enter upon the
written record temporary ordinance
18-25. Any further discussion? Nothing
further. Thank you. Hearing none, please
call the role. Mr. Als, yes. Mr.
Bisjack, yes. Mrs. Kes, yes. Mrs. Hoop,
yes. Mr. Lockenberg, yes. Mr. Skunover,
yes. Mr. Sully, yes. Miss Teener, yes.
Mr. Wing, yes. And Mr. Wolfinger. Yes.
Motion to pass and gross and enter upon
the written record temporary ordinance
18-25 passes 10 to zero. We'll now move
on to the first reading of ordinances
beginning with temporary ordinance
19-25.
An ordinance providing for the issuance
in the sale of notes in the maximum
principal amount of $7 million in
anticipation of the issuance of bonds
for the purpose of paying the cost of
the renovation and rehabilitation of the
city hall building and otherwise
improving the site. Therefore,
um together with all
necessary pertinent pertinent
pertinances, thank you. Pertinent
tendences there too and declared an
emergency finance committee. Um Mr.
Wolfinger and Mr. Sullie. Council member
Wolfinger. That'll be first of three
readings and I will answer that
gentleman's question. Sure. Uh after the
meeting is over. Thank you. If you hang
around. Thank you.
First of three readings on temporary
ordinance
19-25. Temporary ordinance 20-25.
An ordinance to accept the annexation of
5.08 plus or minus acres in the Pleasant
Township and to declare an emergency.
This is through economic de development
committee. Mrs. Hoop and Mrs. Crates.
Council member Hoop. Yes. This is first
of three readings. First of three
readings on temporary ordinance
20-25. Temporary ordinance 21-25. an
ordinance to amend the zoning map um
subject to passage of the annexation of
5.08 plus or minus acres in the Pleasant
Township and to declare an emergency
once again is through economic
development committee Mrs. Hoop and Mr.
Wing. Council member Hoop. Thank you,
Mr. President. This is first of three
readings. First of three readings on
temporary ordinance 21-25.
Temporary Ordinance 22-25,
an ordinance to amend section
1339.13 of the codified ordinances of
the city of Lancaster's entitled
wireless communications
telecommunications. Um, this is through
code enforcement and zoning committee.
Uh, Mr. Lockenberg and Mr. H or Mrs.
Hoop. Council member Luenberg. First of
three readings, please. First of three
readings on temporary ordinance
22-25 tabled legislation. I I'm assuming
we're leaving that on the table. Thank
you. So 24 or excuse me, temporary
ordinance
52-24 will remain on the
table. We now move on to unfinished
business. Is there any unfinished
business before council this
evening? New business. Is there any new
business in front of council this
evening? I I do have the public hearing
on April 21st, 2025 at 6:30 for the
power run tiff incentive districts.
Thank you, Council Member Teener. Yes, I
was Mr. Wolfinger. Could you go ahead
and answer him, sir, since he asked a
question in public um so that everybody
would hear it uh regarding the just so
that since he did ask it in public? No,
that's fine. I have no problem doing
that. May I ask him to repeat the
question?
Sure. Well, sure. I want to make sure I
get it answered. My question was that
you guys know the length of the bonds
and if so, do you know the interest rate
for said bond?
Yes, thank you. Uh first of all, we will
not be going to a bond when for the
first year because if it's a
construction loan and not knowing what
kind
of change orders it might come into
play, we will finance it on a what you
call a bond anticipation note or known
as a ban. And that ban will be uh 12
months in duration and that will be uh
orchestrated by the city auditor. Uh
that will probably not close until we'll
say June 1st in that general time frame.
And that rate we we don't know today,
but the one-year interest rate will
probably be somewhere between three
three and a quarter and and 4% four and
a quarter something in that range
because I can't forecast. It's like
mortgage rates, you can't say what it's
going to be down the road. Does that
help you? Oh, then when that's done,
we'll know what all their costs are and
it could be less than $7 million. It
could be slightly more. And then we will
make a determination approved through
council of how to permanently fund the
remaining amount. If it is uh it could
be a bond, it could be continuation of
annual renewal of our band notes. Uh
there's minimal closing cost to do
those. If we go into a bond, then we'll
have significant closing costs with bond
council and all kinds of stuff we get in
from the legal perspective. Right now,
if we would look at a uh 20-year bond,
you're looking probably around
385 3.9. If you look at a 10-year bond,
it might be uh 3.25, but again, that
changes by the day. The rates have
trended downward slightly. Uh but the
yield curve is still pretty traditional.
Uh we all worry about the impacts of of
the tariffs. We worry about all the
other stuff that's entering our economy.
So I can't forecast that rate for you if
that helps you. Question. Once again,
this is not a question and answer
session. If you want to connect
afterwards, we'd be happy to as far as
that goes. So we we just have to do it
for respective time. Yeah. and I will. I
just don't want to get yelled at. You're
not getting yelled at, Council Member
Skoonover.
No, no offense to to Bob, but the short
non-banker answer is the legislation
that we have in front of us that's in
the all one packet. It's estimated at 6%
20 years is the length just for the
placeholders to go on. And I'll give
this to you. I have this. I'll give it
to you. That's in the packet. I don't do
they have packet full packets on the
table or just I'll give this to you
afterwards. Yeah, the one posted online
has it on there. And and so you know
that 6% rate is a high rate that they
put in there knowing the rate won't go
that high, but you have to have a point
in the sand that you plant your stick
and that's what that's about. But I gave
you current rates.
Thank you. Thanks.
We'll now move on to announcements of
scheduled meetings. Next regular
sessions of council is April 7th, 2025
at 6:30 p.m. here in council chambers
and then again April 21st on 2025 at
6:30 p.m. in council chambers. Special
meetings. I have none. Regularly
scheduled committee meetings. I have
safety committee April 4th at 8 a.m.
City Hall 1897 conference room.
Administrative Services Committee, April
16th at 8 am, City Hall 1897, conference
room. Code Enforcement and Zoning
Committee, April 17th at 7:30 a.m. and
City Hall 1897 conference room. And then
Economic Development Committee, April
24th at 7:30 a.m., City Hall 1897
conference room. Thank you. Reading of
bills. I have MNCO for
$114.52. And then again, MNCO for
$27529.
Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
that we pay the bills. Second. Have a
motion and second to pay the bills. All
those in favor, please signify by saying
I. I. All those opposed, same sign. We
have no need for an executive session
this evening. I will now take a motion
to adjurnn. Mr. President, I'd like to
make that motion. We adjourn. Second.
Okay, we have a motion to second to
adjurnn. All those in favor signify by
saying I. I. All those opposed, same
sign. We are adjourned. Please stay and
sign your legislation before you leave.
Thank you. See the guy
[Music]